<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true rehersall of the honourable [and] tryu[m]phant victory which the defenders of the trueth haue had againste the tyranical and bloodthirsty heape of ye Albanists. Which came to passe withoute the worthye cyttie of Harlam in Holland. the xxv. daye of Marche. 1573. Translated out of Dutch into English, the thyrde day of Apryll: the which copy in Dutch, was printed at Delft, the xxvii day of March laste paste.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1573</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120345</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855544</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855544</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03453)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 639:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true rehersall of the honourable [and] tryu[m]phant victory which the defenders of the trueth haue had againste the tyranical and bloodthirsty heape of ye Albanists. Which came to passe withoute the worthye cyttie of Harlam in Holland. the xxv. daye of Marche. 1573. Translated out of Dutch into English, the thyrde day of Apryll: the which copy in Dutch, was printed at Delft, the xxvii day of March laste paste.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Iones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the. vj. day of Apryll. 1573.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: At Harlam in Holland the. xxvij. day of Marche.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A1,8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21039:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:21039:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
            <p>A true reherſall of the Honorable &amp; Tryu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phant Victory: which the defenders of the Trueth haue had againſte the tyranical and blood thirſty heape of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Albaniſts.</p>
            <p>¶ Which came to paſſe withoute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worthye Cyttie of Harlam in Holland. the xxv. daye of Marche. 1573.</p>
            <p>¶ Tranſlated out of Dutch into Engliſh, the thyrde day of Apryll: the which Copy in Dutch, was Printed at Delft, the xxvii. day of March laſte paſte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PRINTED BY RICHARD IONES</hi> the .vj. day of Apryll. <hi>1573.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21039:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21039:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
            <head>Of ſuch things as are come to paſſe at the ſiege of Harlam in Holland: <date>the xxv. daye of Marche. 1573.</date>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthoughe all thynges (welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) whiche by the grace of God, are come to paſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Citie of Harlam in Holand, are worthye, not by peeces, but from the beginning vnto the end to bee rehearſed, and ſet before the eyes of all men: that the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and worthy works of God therby may bee knowen, and his name for euer magnified &amp; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Notwithſtandynge, (I thought it good) before the whole Diſcourſe and rehearſall of all
<pb facs="tcp:21039:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->theſe thyngs (peraduenture) ſhal bee geuen vnto all Nations and people to bee red, heere ſhortly to noate (&amp; that with trueth,) vnto all ſuch as are louers of the ſame, a notable worke of God, and ſuch a deede of the moſte higheſt, that euen with out eyes, we maye ſee and perceiue that which he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely hath brought to paſſe, the .xxv. Daye of Marche. <hi>1573.</hi> by them of the ſame Citie.</p>
            <p>For, when as that worthy and before named Cytie, had now ben beſieged of the Spaniſh and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baniſſhe power more then three Monethes, and in great diſtreſſe: howbeit, the ennemyes hauynge their head twiſe mightely bruſed and their worthyeſt and ſtouteſt oulde Souldyers, yea &amp; manlyeſt Captaynes we are loſte: ſo that their weakeneſſe and feare ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred
<pb facs="tcp:21039:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->them not any more to geue any aſſault: Beſides that, ſhame and neede forced them ſtyll to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde: For ſhame, they durſte not go away, becauſe that thus long they had alwayes proſpered very well: and beynge nowe come to this Cytie, whiche was the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt and weakeſt in all Holland, and at the firſte, worſte of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded: eyther of Armour, Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyers, or Vittayle, amongſte the reſt, that was to be founde: And therfore, not able (as it weare) to to doo any thyng. And for that cauſe, (as they ſuppoſed) ſhould it be counted vnto them, an euer laſtynge ignomynie and ſhame, with a perpetuall Diſhonour.</p>
            <p>And for neede, they durſte not departe, (for feare) leaſte by the waye, they ſhould be mette with at home, meanynge therfore w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a
<pb facs="tcp:21039:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->contynual Siege, and priuie pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes and treaſon: lyke as before they had recouered other Cyties again, ment in lyke caſe to catch this within their Clawes alſo. But at the laſt, when they of the Cyttie began to be greened ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and were certain, that God dyd manifeſtly vnderſtande their cauſe, and that he was the onely Defender of the ſame, (as hee is in deede, to all innocentes which wholly put their truſte in him:) thei haue often and diuers times gone about with ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drie aſſaultes and Skyrmyſſbes, for to trappe (not onely theirs but alſo Gods Enemies,) in the ſame pittes, which for their Deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, theyr Enemies, had redye dygged and prouyded. And although, that they neuer haue attempted any thynge, but that they haue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by gotten both Honour &amp; prayſe:
<pb facs="tcp:21039:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->yet neuertheleſſe, when God at their great pryde &amp; intollerable Cirrannie and crueltie: and to be ſhorte, at all the wronges whiche thei had vſed day by day, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at length to begreued, with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly behauiour of theſe Blood-hounds ſo that their Houreglaſſe at laſt is runne out and ended:</p>
            <p>For then, the good and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lorde hath delyuered them into the handes of his people, to be taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſnares which they had prepared for the other.</p>
            <p>For, they of the Cyttie aboute ten of the Clocke before Noone, with a ſmal company were gone out of the Cytie to ſkirmiſh with the .xvi. Enſignes of Dutchmen, and the .xv. Enſigns of Wallons, whiche did lye before in the wood at the South ende of the Cytie, from the whiche place, they had purpoſed from that tyme foorth
<pb facs="tcp:21039:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->to batter the Cyttie with ſhotte.</p>
            <p>And thus, they beynge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute in the forenoone, brought ſpeciallie nothynge to paſſe: but marchynge vp and downe a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſpace, and when they ſaw their tyme to retyre, entred into the Cyttie agayne.</p>
            <p>When the Ennemie ſawe this, and ſuppoſynge it too bee good, and all daunger to bee paſte, and all thynges ended for that daye: (after a whyle) gaue hym ſelfe to reſte, and ſette his heart on ſofte grounde. Then (in the meane tyme,) our men makynge them ſelues cheereful and couragious, and hauynge reſpecte vnto their tyme and purpoſe, (and chieflye) vnto their iuſt quarrell: So that of Wallones, Dutchmen, French men, &amp; Engliſhmen: about .ix. or a x. hundreth men, aboute two of the Clocke in the afternoone,
<pb facs="tcp:21039:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->yſſued oute of the Cyttie agayne, and without any ſtoppe or feare, and without any noyſe makyng, ranne ſtrayght vnto their Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. The Enemie, ſeynge that he was taken vnawares, and his Enemies vnlookte for, ſodaynly fallen vppon hym, at the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended hymſelfe very lytle: And at laſte ſeynge hym ſelfe incloſed and ouerrunne, by and by ſought meanes, whiche waye beſt for to eſcape. Our men (to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye,) with burnynge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable boldeneſſe, fell vppon them, and ſo rayſed them oute of their Neſtes and chaſed them, that they ranne thorowe and thorowe the wood, hither and thyther: that of all the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whiche (in deede) beſt kept their ſtandynge, but ſewe eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: And of the Wallones which firſt tooke the flight, there are
<pb facs="tcp:21039:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->ſome runne awaye, ſome: ſlayne with ſhotte, and ſome drowned: being al bereft of their Weapon: and as the moſte parte ſay, about two thouſand men were ſlayne. And it is ſayd alſo, of one Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeur de Luckes, Generall of the Wallons, with other Captaynes ſhould there be ſlaine alſo at that preſent. This beyng done, they haue ouertourned their Tentes and Trenches, and ſet them on fyre, purſuynge them to the laſte man: And then returnyng with great Tryumph &amp; Ioye, brought with them into the Cyttie, fyue Braſen Peeces, with other Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytion: as Headpeeces, Harneſſe, Pikes, Dagges, Swordes and Rapiers, with vittayle and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which was ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>DALBA,</hi> to pay them: and alſo great ſtore and much abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of Apparell.
<pb facs="tcp:21039:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->For at their retyryng to the Citie was heard .viii. of their Dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes herefully ſoundyng, with tenne <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſignes diſplaying, bryngyng <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith them great ſpoyles of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey, Iewelles and Armour, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll kynde of thynges, wherwith <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uery one being loden: with great Ioye, came all cluſtryng into the Cittie. When the Cytizyns, with all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feared the Lord, ſawe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow that they had obtayned the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ictorie, and had put their Foes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> flight, with one conſent gaue <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>artie thankes and praiſes vnto God, that ſo mercifullye of his goodneſſe, had brought the ſame <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o paſſe. This alſo, hath mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d me and reioyſed my hart and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aynde that I (euen of gladneſſe) <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oulde not leaue, but participate this vnto the gentle Reader and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o make manyfeſt and ſet before the eyes of all ſuch as from their hartes doe hate the intollerable
<pb facs="tcp:21039:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->yoke of bondage and Spanyſh t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rannie: and with body and goods ſeeke to withſtande them. The Lorde open the eyes of them that are yet remayni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, that they may acknowledge their vniuſte dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyngs and return from their eui<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and turne vnto the lyuyng God, againſt whom (euen as Giants) they haue waged Battel: tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they with vs and all faithful<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> People maye liue in peace and vnitie from this time forthe for euermore: the whiche God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende vs, and all ſorowfull an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſighinge harts. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>¶ Writen in haſte to all the faithful<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through loue. From Delft <date>the 27 day of Marche. 1573.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>¶ FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21039:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
